Afghanistan Subject Files, Inclusive: 1978-2002; undated, Bulk: 1980-1987
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Afghanistan Subject Files
Inclusive: 1978-2002; undated, Bulk: 1980-1987
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
11
Keston Institute, 1969 -
4 A4 document boxes
Afghanistan Subject Files contain a variety of materials on multiple topics, including military action, international relations, Islam, and general history.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Keston collected documents dating from 1979-2002 on the political and religious climate in Afghanistan.
In 1978, the People’s Democratic Party of Afghanistan took control of the country. Soon thereafter, those opposing the Communist regime launched a civil war. These guerrilla mujahedeen, backed by the United States, fought against the government that was aided by Russia. The country was plunged into turmoil with various leaders assassinated and quickly replaced by the Soviets. Many fled the country, and many more died in the civil war.
Between 1989-1992, President Najibullah, also known as Mohammad Najibullah, tried to calm the civil war and emphasized an Islamic government. However, after Pakistan attacked Jalalabad with the mujahidin and with the dissolution of the Soviet Union, Najibullah was removed from power in 1992. After Saudi Arabia and Iran backed various Afghan militias, fighting increased. In 1994, the Taliban took control of the southern regions of Afghanistan. In 1996, they took Kabul.
The Taliban introduced strict enforcement of Sharia Islamic law and established the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan in 1996. Between 1996 and 2001, al-Qaeda began to emerge. On September 9, 2001, Afghan mujahedeen political and military leader Ahmad Shah Masoud died in the Panjshir Province of wounds inflicted by two suicide bombers. Two days later, the United States was attacked, prompting an American invasion of Afghanistan to remove the Taliban from power.
Scope and Content
Afghanistan General Subject Files consist of newspaper clippings, periodicals, background reports, and bibliographic references.
The materials range from 1978-2002, with a majority from 1980-1987. The collection pertains primarily to military actionDLthe majority between Afghanistan, Russia, and religious mujahedeen guerillasDLas well as international relations (mostly Russia, with some England and United States) and general history. Notable individuals in the collection include Babrak Karmal, Mohammad Najibullah, Jacques Abouchar, and Ahmad Shah Masoud. The files on religion deal primarily with Islam.
Afghanistan Denominational Subject Files range from 1978-2002, and include Judaism and Christianity. There is a noticeable lack of content from any particular denomination for a variety of reasons. Because materials related to Islam cannot be separated from political subjects, that information is contained in the religion folders in the Afghanistan General Subject Files.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Afghanistan materials in folders in no particular order. They have been organized by specific categories and denominations and subsequently arranged thematically and chronologically.
Currently, the Afghanistan Subject Files are arranged in two series: I. General and II. Denominational.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 11.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Abouchar, Jacques, 1931-; Karmal, Babrak.; Masud, Amadsho, 1953-2001.; Najib, 1947-1996.
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Taliban.
Places
Afghanistan -- Armed Forces.; Afghanistan -- Foreign relations -- Soviet Union.; Afghanistan -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Afghanistan -- History -- 1989-2001.; Afghanistan -- History -- 2001-; Afghanistan -- History -- Soviet occupation, 1979-1989.; Afghanistan -- Politics and government -- 1973-1989.; Afghanistan -- Politics and government -- 1989-2001.; Afghanistan -- Politics and government -- 2001-; Soviet Union -- Foreign relations -- Afghanistan.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Afghanistan.
Subjects
Christians -- Afghanistan.; Freedom of religion -- Afghanistan.; Freedom of the press -- Afghanistan.; Guerrillas -- Afghanistan.; Human rights -- Afghanistan.; Islamic law -- Afghanistan.; Jews -- Afghanistan.; Women (Islamic law) -- Afghanistan.; Women's rights -- Afghanistan.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Periodicals.
- General, 1978-2002; undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series is of the General Subject Files of Afghanistan, including historical background, important individuals, and the military. It is in good condition.
  - History (1 of 3), 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History (2 of 3), 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History (3 of 3), 1986-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Individuals (Abouchar-Zia), 1980-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Government, 1980-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Military (1 of 5), 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Military (2 of 5), 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Military (3 of 5), 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Military (4 of 5), 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Military (5 of 5), 1990-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Espionage, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Emigration, 1980-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Laws, Constitution, Oppressive Practices, 1981-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Prisons, Labor Camps, Amnesties, 1981-2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - International Relations (1 of 2), 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - International Relations (2 of 2), 1986-2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Amnesty International, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Religion (1 of 2), 1978-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Religion (2 of 2), 1992-2002; undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ideology, Communism, Propaganda, Philosophy, 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Communism and Religion, 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Health, 1981-2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Information Services, TV, Radio, Press, 1981-1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Arts, Architecture, Music, 1981-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Women, 1989-1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Youth, 1980-1999 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Denominational, 1978-2002; 2
  This series contains one folder on the denominations of both Christianity and Judaism in Afghanistan. It is in good condition.
  - Christianity and Judaism: General, 1978-2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)